[Music]
Good evening everyone. Everyone, welcome
to the July 14th Finance Committee. I am
your host,
Corey Skunover. Uh, if you have noticed,
the agenda's changed a tad. So, just as
a for a brief rundown all the new
resolutions and ordinances we're going
to go over, I'm just going to kick it
directly to the chair of whatever
committee it's coming through and then
you can choose how you want to introduce
it and then hopefully you have someone
from the city department to discuss it
if you need. So, do we have any
questions before we get started?
Great. So, we'll start out new
resolutions, temporary resolutions 6325
coming through public works. Uh, Miss
Tener,
>> yes. This is a grant that we're applying
for that we've just kind of found out
about uh recently. It needs to be
actually suspended and voted on tonight.
It's due August the 8th, and it's
regarding the intersection of um Pearson
uh Memorial, the walkway there to make
it safer. Uh the grant is for $400,000
and our 20% match would be uh 80, yes,
$80,000. Uh it does need to be in by the
ETH and we need to make things safer for
pedestrians. And if Carrie would like to
talk about the rightway,
>> I'm more than happy to talk about it,
but it would not be nearly as fun as
having Jeff Be, our assistant city
engineer, come up and give you
engineering specifics.
>> Thanks, Jeff.
He was hiding.
>> Yeah. This uh what we're doing is we're
uh wanting to put a grant application in
to apply for acquiring the rideway for
the Memorial Pierce Walks project. We're
currently um under design. It's probably
about 50% complete design. uh rightway
plans are done and it's the the new
walks from Arlington to Whittier along
Memorial Drive and then also down um
Pierce down to uh River Valley Drive
there. And so what this grant is is it's
going to pay for we're planning on using
federal money. So we're making sure we
have all the boxes checked so we uh
qualify for that federal money. So we
have to make sure we acquire the right
away for all the federal standards. And
so this grant will actually pay for um
the cost of acquisition itself plus the
cost of all the land. And there's you
know uh quite a few permanent and
temporary rightway takes that be needed
for this project. So this is uh applying
for a grant to acquire the rightway for
the project. And if it does pass
tonight, uh we'll have to have extra
legislation to move the money for the
80,000.
>> Yeah, we Yeah, we just recently got the
grant applications in and they're due
the eth. So, we have to kind of jump on
it kind of quick.
>> Any questions?
>> What's the What's the ultimate endgame?
What's the project look like at the end
once it's complete? Well, once it's
done, there's going to be uh a new
crosswalk, three new crosswalks on
Memorial Drive, one at the Kroger
entrance, one down there, um across with
the the little road that comes out where
the uh one of the outlets for the the
apartment complex back there, there's
that with the light with the traffic
signal is. And then down at Whittier,
there will be a crossing. And there's
going to um be sidewalks on both sides
of the road from Arlington all the way
down to to Whittier and then also on
only one side of the road down Pierce,
but it'll it'll go from Memorial Drive
all the way down to uh Riverside Drive.
>> As someone who's crossed Memorial Drive
in the dark, I thank you.
>> Why would you cross Memorial Drive?
>> Because I locked my keys in my car.
>> Okay. I just wanted
>> and my cell phone and everything else.
>> Thanks for clarifying that.
>> Any other questions?
>> And you said you were asking for
suspension. I have Mr. Lur.
>> Mr. Lock Murphy. Yes. Okay. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Uh we have next temporary
resolution 6425 coming through economic
development. Mrs. Hoop.
>> Yes. This is um the same grant um but
the port authority is going to be
applying for $700,000 with a $140,000
match
um paid for by the port authority. Um
and it's going to fund design and
engineering for improvements to
campground road. And if anyone has any
other questions Oh, we also have to
suspend because of the same deadline.
But Stephanie, if you have anything else
to add?
>> Yep. just that like Jeff said, the
application came out Monday, last
Monday, but um for the 20% match, we're
going to use the TIFF funds. The port
will front the money because we um if
the all the TIFFs pass, um the TIF
probably won't have enough money. So,
we'll um front it and then we'll get
reimbursed down the road. And we're
going to be using this for design work
on Campground Road.
Any
questions?
And I have so yes for suspension and I
have Miss Crates as your second.
>> Yep.
>> Yeah. Great.
All right. Temporary resolution 6525
that is coming through the finance
committee. So I guess that's me.
Um
yeah. Yes. I did see Miss Hamilton here.
So, we're going to move some funds.
>> Uh we're just going to appropriate from
my cash uh balance for
some extra refunds that we need to
finish off, help us get through the end
of the year. I had a couple of
businesses that hit us with some refunds
that were a little over $200,000
combined. So, portion of that is to help
get us through the rest of the year. And
then I am looking to move our backup
server to the cloud. We've been kind of
gimping along on the one that we've had
for quite a while. It's an oldie that
Trish was on and we're just about giving
it all that she's got, but we're we're
we're about done. So, this is going to
allow us um enhance security,
you know, access and um just help us
have more memory for what we need to do
in in income tax. So,
>> any questions from anyone on that piece?
So, it says 250 for the refunds and then
135 for the software.
>> Yep. And obviously what doesn't get used
in refunds at the end of the year goes
back to the cash balance. So, I just
wanted to be a little
proactive just in case um we have to
make it through the October 15th
extensions and that's when and well
through November as well. And sometimes
we get some businesses towards that end
that'll be realizing what their balance
sheets are. So,
>> okay.
All right. I have three readings on
that. Mr. Sully will be my second.
>> Okay.
>> Good.
>> Yep.
>> All right. Thank you. Temporary
resolution 6625 that's coming through
economic development, Miss Hoop.
>> Um, yes. This is to begin the annexation
process for 163 acres from Greenfield
Township
and I am asking for suspension
and Mr. Wing is going to be my second.
>> Does anybody have any questions?
Stephanie, you wanna
>> I can always add any more. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, this is like like um as we've
said, 163 acres um 65 on the east side
of 33 and the remainder on the west side
of 33 within the Rockmill Industrial
Park right on Wilson. And it is going to
be zoned advanced manufacturing. Um, and
then we're already marketing the east
side and down the road we'll market the
other side as we um begin to learn more
about the site. We need to do a little
due diligence.
>> Okay. Are we good? Uh, you're going to
ask for suspension with Mr. Wing as your
second.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah.
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
>> Stephanie,
>> just wanted to give the reason for that.
It's an expedited type two annexation
which requires us to follow the the
revised code timeline. So we have 20
days from the date the petition is filed
and the petition was filed on the 10th I
believe. So
>> I feel like we're all should be experts
on the on these annexations. I feel like
we're doing one every time we're sitting
here. Is that is that right? Because
that's how it feels.
>> No. So
>> you don't think we should be experts or
that's what you're
>> we're like we're not doing enough of
them.
>> We're not doing one every time you meet.
Okay. The issue is there are multiple
steps in the process, right? And so
every time you meet, yes, you are doing
something for one of them along the way
in that process, but they're not new
annexations every single time you meet.
So
>> all right, that's semantics I feel. But
>> we do think you're experts, though.
>> Okay, we have to be experts at
something. I was hoping. All right. Uh,
any other resolutions that we have? No.
So, we're going to move on to
ordinances, temporary ordinance 3125
that is coming through code enforcement
and zoning. Mr. Sully.
>> Hi. So, we're going to be uh updating
our building code, our codes and zoning
for short-term rentals. Uh, there's
going to be a presentation tonight.
Chasine, I don't know if you want to
talk now or
u
briefly.
>> Good evening. Yes, this is just um a
proposed code for short-term rentals
that we would add to our current zoning
code and then I'll be doing a
presentation on the at the regular
meeting shortly.
>> Okay. So, we'll save all that. So, we do
question and answer after presentation.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So, we'll touch on that then and
then I have three readings and Mrs. Hoop
as your second. Yes.
>> Okay.
I'm like speeding through. I don't have
time to write notes. We're going to
meeting minutes should be interesting.
Uh temporary ordinance 3225 that is
coming through economic development.
Miss Soup.
>> Yes. This is another annexation.
Um it's to accept the I think it's like
half of an acre from um Pleasant
Township on Sheridan Drive.
Um
and then this one is two readings
with Mrs. Kates as my second
and then there's a there's another piece
after it. I don't know if you want me
to.
>> Okay. So 32 and 33
>> Yeah. or for the same.
>> Yeah. So 33 um just changes the zoning
to manufactured zoning
and it's just a part of the enteration
process.
>> Did you do manufactured?
>> Well, multif family. I'm sorry. You're
right. It's multif family. It's not
manufacturer.
>> It's the cast.
>> Yeah.
>> It's it's residential. It's that little
island on the uh Sheridan Drive um
housing development. So,
last last couple steps and they're both
going to be two readings.
>> Okay. And as Stephanie mentioned, it's
not a different annexation. It's
>> step 72 and 73 of Euing Woods
annexation.
>> Yeah. Yep.
>> Okay. So, that covers 32 and 33. Anyone
have any questions on those? No.
Temporary ordinance 3425. It's also
coming through economic development,
Mrs. Hoop.
>> Okay. So, this is a companion piece to
the resolution 6625.
Um, so this is to accept the annexation
of the 163 acres back onto Campground
Road.
>> Okay.
>> And it's also going to be suspended and
wing will be my second.
>> Okay. Anything
you want to add?
>> No.
>> So, the companion piece to 6625,
you're not a different annexation.
That's
>> right.
>> I'm just going to run with that.
>> You are an expert.
>> I'm just going to run with that line all
night. Okay.
Suspension. You said Mr. Wing.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Temporary ordinance 3525
is coming through administrative
services. Mr. Luenberg.
>> Yes. I'd like to ask uh our safety
service director to introduce her uh
administrative assistant uh to describe
what we're talking about here.
>> I'll take care of that as the law
director. Um Jackie is our court
administrator in the Fairfield County
Municipal Court and she's here tonight
on behalf of Judge Fields. Uh much
better looking and much more concise. So
everybody, you know, be glad we have
her. Um but she's here tonight because
the the court is uh having an unexpected
retirement this year. Um the court's
director of probation services actually
gave notice um not too long ago that she
was going to be retiring unexpectedly.
Um and the court needs to fill her
position. And all they really need from
you is to change the name in the
management pay ordinance from the title
that it currently is director of
probation services to the new title
which is going to be grants manager and
writer or grants writer and manager if
I'm saying that correctly
>> administrator. Um the goal is to the
goal was to remove some of those
probation services from the position so
that it could focus exclusively on
grants and then also obviously um when
you take away those responsibilities you
can reduce the amount of pay that is
that is going to be paid. Um so in order
for them to start advertising for the
position they need to be able to put the
position's name into writing right into
the advertisement. Um, and the goal is
to, you know, keep the keep the
expectations in line with what the job
is actually going to be. So, I'll let
Jackie answer any other questions you
may have.
>> Any questions? Um, ordinarily, I get to
hide behind Judge Fields. So, they are
at conference this week. So, I am here
to answer any questions you may have.
Um, if any of you have worked with
Tamara in the past, she is a dynamo as
far as applying for, getting grants,
managing grants. She has just continued
to accept more and more job duties over
her tenure with the court and we'd like
to realign that and just focus mainly on
applying for grants and managing the
grants. So that's that's why we're here
before you tonight as Stephanie said.
>> Thank you. Thank you for the
explanation. Um in relation to the other
duties that you say that are going away
related to probation. Yes. Um who who
would be assuming those and would there
be any companion pieces of legislation
that might resolve? So, currently our
chief probation officer, Matt Shine, is
going to be taking on some of some more
of the personnel duties that Tamara had
been doing. And the other probation
officers that work directly with her for
the grant programs, the drug court, the
veterans court, the mental health court,
and the opportunity court, they'll be
taking on some of those duties as well.
We would kind of like to see how things
go the next six months. And as we work
towards the pay ordinance for 2026, then
we can re-evaluate where we would like
to do possibly some job description and
salary adjustments there.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other questions?
>> Thanks, Jackie.
>> Um because of the nature, we don't have
any additional meetings in July. We'd
like to suspend the second and third
readings.
>> Okay.
>> And uh Councilman Bischek will be my
second.
>> Okay.
We have any more ordinances that we need
to discuss?
Seeing none, I am open for department
updates. Anybody have a department
update?
No, I scared everybody to the You're
making him do a department update.
Perfect.
>> He had a departmental update that he
wanted to share really badly tonight.
So, we'll let him come back up.
>> Yeah, it looks like it. Yeah. Kurt
doesn't let him out very often, so he's
using all the time he can.
>> Yeah. Well, I don't know if everybody's
aware, but we got a raise grant earlier
in the year. We were awarded it, but it
was put on hold. And we just recently
been notified that the the federal
government, they're ready to move
forward with a raise grant. And this RA
grant is to fund a feasibility study for
the east side industrial connector,
which the concept of that is it'll be a
a brand new road, brand new corridor,
and it's going to start um it's going to
parallel US22
and it's going to connect the 22 um east
of Memorial or West Memorial and then go
east and to the east side of town to and
come back into 22 east of the soccer
fields. And the idea of this is to take
a lot of that um truck traffic and
commercial traffic and route it around
downtown rather than through downtown.
And another purpose of this is to make
it easier to get to the industrial area
out there on the east side to try to
help develop that area, the industrial
park on the east side of town. So, um,
right now we're moving forward and we're
in the, um, doing the grain agreement
and we just had a a conversation with
them and all the stuff we got to do and
all the stuff they got to do. And the
grant agreement will probably take about
four months to uh, get accomplished. And
then once we do get the grant agreement,
we'll um, start doing RFQS and putting
together timelines, etc. to actually uh,
go out and get a consultant to help us
do the feasibility study for this
project. Any
questions for Mr. Beard?
>> No. All right. Thank you.
>> Appreciate it.
Anybody else?
Miss Woody,
>> I just have a few updates that I'd like
to update everyone. If you didn't
notice, the work on city hall has
officially started. Uh the contractors
have been there for just over a week
now. Uh scaffolding starts going up next
week. Um, they're hoping to have all the
scaffolding up and out and and all the
sidewalks reopen for the art walk, which
leads me into point number two. If
everyone noticed the alley, I know that
I've been getting a lot of questions
about the alley. The contractor was
hoping to have it done last week.
However, with all of our rain, it keeps
getting delayed. They are working as
fast as they can to try and have the the
alley complete before the art walk as
well. Um, so again, I'm sure you're
getting questions because I know I'm
getting a lot of questions. If you
didn't see my email earlier today, I
also wanted to update you. Um, city
council graciously allowed us to enter
into a contract with Fairfield Medical
Center this year to offer free uh urgent
care clinic hours to our city employees
free of charge. And I sent out the email
update this morning, but also wanted to
let you know on council floor that so
far in the first four months of
operation under this contract, they have
treated 381
of our uh individuals, saving our health
insurance over $6,000 so far in four
months and saving our employees $9,500
in co-pays. So, I thought that was an
awesome thing to share with you. uh also
received an update uh this afternoon
about our mental health counseling and
they have also seen 30 people so far um
for free mental health counseling. So
again, thank you council for uh allowing
us to enter into those contracts. I
think that it's a great service that
we're offering to our employees and I
thought that that would be great to
share with you.
>> Very good. Any questions?
No. Any more departmental updates?
Seeing none, meeting prep for this
evening, Mr. Porter.
Thank you, Chairman Skoonover.
I almost called you Chairman Wolfinger.
Uh, tonight for the tonight's meeting,
we have a presentation by our city
planner, Chas Carter, uh, related to the
short proposed short-term rental um code
to be included in our zoning code. And
we also have a public hearing on the
Euing Woods um um LLC um zoning map
amendment.
>> Okay,
>> excellent.
>> Perfect. Thank you. Uh other discussion
items, Mr. Mayor?
>> Yes, Mr. Chairman. Um,
one of the things I have a pleasure of
doing is uh periodically appointing uh
individuals uh to various boards and
commissions within the city. At the end
of this month, we have two uh vacancies
occurring on the board of zoning
appeals. Uh Rebecca Anderson, who's a
long-term
um member of that board, uh has agreed
to stay on. Uh Jim Bonson uh generously
agreed to stay on should we find no
replacement. I I I'm happy to report
that I asked several people and Tom
James, former city council person, has
agreed to uh be appointed to that
position. Those positions do require
council confirmation. I invited Tom here
tonight and Rebecca. What I should tell
you is Rebecca's in Chicago. Grandchild
number two is being delivered. So, she
wanted to be here. She agreed to be
here, but with the caveat that
grandchildren come first. So, she's not
here tonight. I I did send you her
resume. She's well qualified for that
position. I strongly recommend her and I
think uh if anyone has any questions of
Tom, he is here presently, but I do
think most of you know him. Um
so, with that said, I would be asking
during the new business portion of
tonight's meeting for you to uh confirm
those appointments to the board of
zoning appeals.
And I'm happy to answer any questions.
Any questions? So, we want to see Tom's
face at the podium.
>> Yes.
>> Oh, there he is. You were block I was
blocked. So, now I saw you can sit down.
>> I know that my appointment might be a
little contentious because many of you
know me and I'm hoping that some of you
will get past some of that. And uh I
will very much appreciate the
opportunity to do this. I've been
compassionate about this city for a long
long time after having served four years
on this uh this legislative body and I'm
looking forward to be part of the board
of zoning appeals and doing whatever we
can to keep this city going in a good
direction and and in a very good
direction as well. So do you have any
questions?
>> No questions but just a thank you for
your willingness to serve. You're
welcome. Yep.
>> Thank you Tom. Anything else for
finance?
No. I will ask for a motion. We adjourn.
>> So moved.
>> Motion is second. We are adjourned.
Thank you.
>> The regular meeting of Lancaster City
Council will commence promptly at 6:30.
What time is it?
Hi, this is Anna Tobin from the Senior
Hub, your local Meals on Wheels
provider. We provide inhome services to
reduce isolation and hunger while
empowering caregivers in their role of
caring for a family member or friend.
This July, we are once again honored to
be chosen by the Buckeye Automotive
Family Buckeye Cares program. Buckeye
will make a generous donation for every
car sold this month. From all of us at
the senior hub and the ones we provide
for, we say thank you.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 740-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
[Music]
to accept the things we cannot change.
The courage to change the things we can.
And finally, the wisdom to know the
difference. I now call the January or
excuse me, the July I wish it was
January, the July 14th uh 2025 Lancaster
City Council meeting to order. Please
join me in the pledge of allegiance. I
pledge allegiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands, one nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als here.
>> Mr. Bisch here.
>> Mrs. Kra here.
>> Mrs. Hoop
>> here.
>> Mr. Luxenberg
>> Mr. Skunover
>> here.
>> Mr. Sully
>> Miss Teener
>> here.
>> Mr. W
>> Please let the record reflect nine
members of city council are present. We
currently do have an opening uh due to
the resignation at the last meeting of
Councilman Wolfinger. Uh we now move to
the reading and disposing of the
journal.
>> Um I have regular meeting minutes dated
June 23rd, 2025.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to receive
and file the journal. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. We now
move on to the reports of city
officials.
>> I have email dated June 25th, 2025
regarding Lancaster City Council at
large vacancies submitted by law
director Stephanie Hall. Email dated
June 25th, 2025 regarding pack property
tax elimination not being on November
ballot submitted by Mayor Mcdon
McDaniel. Email dated June 27th, 2025
regarding the city of Lancaster 2024
comprehensive annual financial report
submitted by um Auditor Nettles. Email
dated June 30th, 2025 regarding July
planning commission submitted by city
planner Chas Carter. Email dated July
3rd, 2025. Uh regarding short-term
rentals, submitted by city planner
Chasine Carter. Email data July 3rd,
2025 regarding shortterm resol rental
rentals presentation submitted by um
President Council President Jeff Porter.
Email data July 7th, 2025. City Hall's
clock bell tower submitted by service
safety director Carrie Woody.
Email dated July 9th, 2025 regarding the
upcoming mean council special
presentation submitted by city planner
Chasen Carter. Email dated July 11, 2025
regarding board of zoning appeals
submitted by Mayor Don McDaniel. And
lastly, email dated July 14th, 2025
regarding parks department budget for
2026 submitted by Mr. Als.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials. Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to receive
and file the reports of city officials.
All those in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. We'll now
move on to communications.
>> I have email dated June 24, 2025
regarding city Lancaster City Council at
large vacancies submitted by Deputy
Director of Fairfield County Board of
Elections, Jane Hanley. Series of emails
regarding public records request at
environmental site at assessment
submitted by staff scientist Colin
McUade of TAC Terracon. That's all I
have.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the communications.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to receive
and file the communications. All those
in favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign. We will
now move on to the portion of our agenda
for presentations. Uh this evening we
have a presentation by our um city
planner Chasyn Carter regarding um a
proposed shortterm rental code.
>> Are you are you going to have some
slides? I'll get out of the way so
people can turn the lights down.
All right. Good evening. Thank you all
for giving me an opportunity to present
the proposed code for short short-term
rentals.
>> Can you see Chaz?
>> Yes.
So, a little background behind the code.
Um, as you know, in September of 2023,
Lancaster adopted a new zoning code, and
there was um a section that was reserved
for short-term rentals. However, it
wasn't included in that code um due to
the legislation going through the state.
Sorry. Um that legislation is still
pending with the state and with this
lack of regulation. Um we are finding
that some of the short-term rental
owners are not submitting their lodging
taxes to the city income tax department.
Um which as you know by law is required.
Um these taxes are used to support
nonprofits such as the Fairfield County
Visitors Bureau and the Decorative Arts
Center. two agencies that I think we can
all agree um help us create a solid
economy in our downtown Lancaster.
Um the zoning office also receives
several phone calls um sporadically from
interested parties um that are trying to
establish a short-term rental and
they're just looking for some kind of
guidance.
So, I thought the best way to go through
the code was just section by section. um
11:31.
This is what is required in the zoning
clearance permit. Section A establishes
that a zoning clearance permit is needed
to operate a short-term rental in
Lancaster. The corresponding sections
state that a separate permit will be
needed for each dwelling unit and that a
copy of that permit must be maintained
and available on site. Section B
establishes that each permit will be
effective until December 31st of the
calendar year of issuance. Section C
states that a renewal application is due
by the first Monday in November prior to
the expiration date.
Section 113102 establishes that the
mayor of Lancaster will determine the
fee schedule and section A states that
any lodging tax will be paid directly to
the city income tax department.
state or list our application
requirements. These are pretty standard
of our zoning applications as well. Um
with things like the address of
short-term rentals, the type of
dwelling, the name of the contact
information for the applicant, the name
of the local host or the emergency
contact that can respond within an hour
if they're different they're different
individuals. the maximum number of
occupants that the applicant is trying
to establish
and the maximum number of motor vehicles
including garage space, two in the
driveway and two on street parking. A
specific number of parking is not
required in the central business
district if the premises are within
1,000 ft of on street parking or public
parking facility. the required off
streetet and central business um
district parking aligns with our current
zoning code chapter 1143.11.
Um it's also in our requirements to have
a labeled site plan with an aerial photo
that kind of identifies where these
parking spaces will be and then a floor
plan that shows the locations of the
bedrooms. This will help with our
occupancy and zoning compliance.
It also um requires a copy of the
background check for the applicant,
local host, and property manager if
these are separate individuals.
Section B establishes that any change in
information in the application or
renewal should be reported to our
offices within 10 days of the change.
Section C establishes that any change in
owner or lease holder shall void the
current zoning permit. This aligns with
our current standards that a new tenant
or change of business would have to get
new permits and occupancy.
sets forth some standards for short-term
rentals. Um on-site parking shall only
be in spaces designated on approved site
plan except for the central business
district.
No advertising or signage will appear on
the exterior or on the exterior shall be
permitted. And then security cameras
shall be installed on the exterior of
the property or in communal spaces such
as living room or kitchen. No cameras
shall be placed in bedrooms or
bathrooms.
The short-term rentals shall not
shall not house sex offenders, be rented
by the hour, are used for any sexually
oriented businesses.
The short-term applicant short-term
rental applicant must obtain an
occupancy permit from the city building
department prior to renting the
premises. The occupancy permit will help
establish compliance with state and
local fire and building laws.
Short-term rentals shall not adversely
affect the character of the neighborhood
in a manner that disturbs the peace and
they must be maintained in a manner that
remains free from zoning, building or
international property maintenance code
violations.
The grounds for a denial of a permit
would be if the applicant submits an
incomplete application or renewal and or
fails to pay the required fee. If the
applicant makes a material
misrepresentation of facts. If the
short-term rental premises has pending
zoning, building or international
property maintenance code or other
regulatory violations. or if the
applicant or short-term rental premises
have a documented history of nuisance
behavior or criminal activity that
endangers neighborhood or public safety.
is the revocation of a permit.
It establishes that a short-term rental
permit may be revoked and prohibit the
application or local host from operating
a short-term rental or reapplying for a
zoning clearance permit for a period of
6 months if one of the following. If
there's any violation of any of the
requirements set forth in section 113103
or section 113104 of the codified
ordinances. if they fail to permit the
city planner or designate the building
official that's going to cover the
occupancy um to inspect the premises to
verify compliance with the provisions of
the chapter in accordance with section
115506 of the codified ordinances or if
they fail to register with the city
income tax department or failing to pay
the lodging tax or fees required by the
codified ordinances
or a higher revised Code
lays out the appeal of denial or
revocation, an appeal from an
administrative official to the board of
zoning appeals in accordance with the
provisions of section 115707
of the codified ordinances. And 1131.99
establishes the penalty that any persons
who violate the provisions of this
chapter shall be guilty of a misdemeanor
of the fourth degree on the first
offense and a misdemeanor of the second
degree for each offense thereafter.
My last slide just kind of gives a draft
timeline um pending dependent on the
approval by city council and and if
there's um any kind of revisions that
need to be made. But the planning and
zoning office would like to have time to
send out letters and applications to all
the existing owners, set up an open
house for short-term owners and hosts to
walk them through the process and answer
any questions. Um, and then kind of set
a timeline that's already established in
this code for having applications due
and fees due by November 3rd. Uh then um
by the end of December we will have
those 2026 permits issued.
>> Okay, any questions?
>> We'll turn back on the lights
question.
[Music]
Do we have any questions from council
members at this time?
Council member Skunover, I know we
talked about this earlier, but we saw an
email that had the application.
I know that you said that that is still
going through some changes. So,
>> yeah, that's a checklist that we'll hand
out with the applications that kind that
lets them know like what needs to be
included.
Okay. And I get the idea that we have
some owners that want some guidance, but
can you give us an idea how many
short-term short-term rentals we
currently have?
>> I believe that we have
>> 42. Okay. Thanks, Janette. We have 42
currently operating in the city.
>> Miss Happerfield, would you like to come
forward because there may be questions
so you can introduce yourself.
Should I re should I rephrase? I'm
sorry, Jonette. Go ahead.
>> I'm Jonet Habberfield. I'm the executive
director of Visit Fairfield County.
That's the tourism office that um this
the funds from the lodging tax or 100%
of our funding. So, we promote the
county including the city for people to
come and visit.
>> Thank you,
>> council members.
So, we have 42.
They come and go because people can take
their rentals on and off the platform.
So at at the most we've had as many as
42 that are renting their units as many
as a 100 nights per year. So um and that
was actually what I looked at today that
some of them have rented them 100 nights
so far this year. So it could
potentially be double that per unit. So
it's a pretty significant amount of of
properties. Okay,
my other questions. I'm might have to
wait till we have the application.
>> Council, other members that may have
questions?
>> Yes, council member Hoop.
>> Um,
so the of the 42 that you know you have,
how many of them are paying taxes?
>> That would be a better question for Amy
because it changes periodically.
>> Um, I would say
>> I don't know, at one point it was only
like 3%. That's countywide. I know it
was low.
>> So, um, you know, there there is I don't
know if you guys are familiar with this,
but there's a 3% lodging tax on the
county level and then there's an
additional 3% lodging tax for the city.
So, it doesn't matter to me where the
funding comes from. You know, I just
look at the total numbers more so than
just what's at the city. So maybe
>> to me
>> um like Janette said
there's no telling because for us right
now there is not a mechanism in place to
track these. It has literally been me
since I took over getting on the
platforms and looking oh I want to book
a place in Lancaster in July. Who's
going to pop up? So um
like she said it it fluctuates. We have
some that are very diligent about
sending in their things every month and
others that are below the radar. They
don't use platforms. Maybe they use word
of mouth. Um, as you can tell, it's just
very underregulated here. And it's been
it's it's been difficult. I mean, for
all of us to try to figure out a good
system to make sure they're getting
their money, that I'm not spending, you
know, half a day on VRBO and Airbnb
looking to to see who's who's not and
then and then that is, you know, then
you got to try to figure out who they
are, where they are, and it's a it's a
lot of work.
Director Hamilton, if I might. Um, and
when we're talking about the tax itself.
Yes.
>> That tax is being paid by the
individuals renting, not not the not the
homeowners.
>> You go to the holiday in, it's the exact
same tax. If you're staying there under
30 days, it's a 3% for us, for the city,
it's a 3% tax.
>> Thank you. Council member Hoop. Yeah,
just to follow up, I know, well, I think
I know in larger cities those platforms
automatically collect tax.
>> They do. Is there a way for you to
solicit?
>> We have tried. They will not. I know
Athens is having the same issue. It has
to be a huge volume. There was a piece I
know in um the house for the state that
they were trying to get that portion of
it to mandate that those platforms
collect for us. But I I haven't seen
where it's moved.
>> Yeah, it's still in the house. There are
actually three different bills that are
addressing this at the state level. Um,
you know, one of them, of course, we
don't support which takes away house
rules. So, you guys couldn't do anything
about them. And then there are two other
ones that are pretty similar that um as
an association of convention visitors
bureaus, we support. And this is mostly
about safety and equity. you know, we
need to know who they are and and where
they are. But also, the hotels have been
collecting this tax for decades, and
it's not fair that if you stay in a
hotel, you have to pay the tax. If you
stay in a short-term rental, you don't.
But um in terms of locating them, we do
have a dashboard now that I'm going to
be able to share um with Chelin's
department that helps us identify them.
It doesn't necessarily give us the
owner's contact information. So, I'm in
full support of, hey, get their contact
information because because of our lack
of hotel rooms here in Lancaster, we try
to put every opportunity for a place for
people to sleep on our website, but we
spend as much time as Amy does trying to
find them so that we can put them on our
website so that a visitor knows where
they can stay. So, it's a vicious circle
and this would eliminate a lot of that
problem, but also make it equitable for
the hotel property owners and um you
know, residential property owners. And
the safety issue, I like the idea of
there being inspections because
honestly, we have identified units that
are in Lancaster that I will not put on
our website because they're not in safe
locations. So, you know, I would know
that if there was an occupancy permit
issued and if safety standards were
being applied, uh, just like they would
if a hotel was a new hotel came to be,
there would be an occupancy permit done
and fire inspections and all kinds of
other things that would be much more
safer for our visitors.
>> I think Council Member Hoops wrapped up
her questions. Anybody else? Council
member Bisjack.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. President. Um, on the
subject of public safety, I mean, how
many bagged actors, if for lack of a
better term, are in the short-term
rental business in the city of
Lancaster? You know, how prevalent of an
issue is it?
>> I only am aware of one property that has
been problematic and the city's
addressing that issue. I mean, it's a
building that's right downtown that
should not be.
>> And and I have one more question, Mr.
President.
>> Yes. Thank you. Uh, and then on the
subject of inspections, and I apologize
if you stated this already, but I just
want to make sure it's clear. How often
will you be inspecting the properties
for safety?
>> So, there will be an initial um
inspection, occupancy inspection and
zoning. Um and then annually we'll do a
zoning kind of checkup.
>> Okay. Thank you. Um Miss Carter, if you
would stay. I have a question related to
the parking requirements. Okay.
>> Will you go through those with with me
and just give them to me once again? So,
units that are not located within the
central business district, what are
their parking requirements?
>> So, they are they can have parking in
their garage and their two in their
driveway and then they can count two um
on street parking as well.
>> So, so are they required to have all of
those available or is what is the
>> that's like the Yeah, that that would be
like the maximum.
>> Okay. So what what would would be the
requirement to have a unit that's not in
the central business district? How many
spaces would they have to have?
>> Um so we would have I mean I guess four
and then if they had a garage they could
use that space as well
going to have to have I guess what I'm
getting at is will they have to have
five spaces to get a unit approved or
can they have something less than that?
>> Um they would if they don't have a
garage there wouldn't be five. the two
in the driveway, the off two I guess two
off streetet, two on street parking
would be counted. So, two off streetet.
Um, and then similar codes, a lot of
codes that I've looked into, they will
require a parking spot or even a parking
spot and a half per bedroom. So, our
code is a little less restrictive than
that. So, if they don't have a driveway
and they have no off- streetet parking
and there's only on street parking
available, would a unit be approved?
>> That that would be something that we'd
have to take into consideration. It
might be something that has to go to the
board of zoning appeals to be approved.
Um, and the board of zoning appeals does
see a lot of cases for parking and they
will work um with the applicants and and
see what makes sense, I guess, in the in
the area that they're in.
>> Okay. Thank you. Any further questions
from council members on the presentation
this evening? Council member Sie.
>> So, what we're proposing here is pretty
consistent with what all the other
cities in Ohio have done. Um, there's
differences in every code, but it's for
the most part pretty consistent. There's
some that are more restrictive. There
are some that that are equal. Um, and
there's some that don't have any at all.
So,
>> Okay.
>> Thank you. Thank you. Any further
questions at this time,
>> Council Member Hoop? Um
what would be um have you landed on um
fees for the application and the
renewals?
>> Yes. So the initial um application would
be 150 and that's consistent with our
commercial zoning that we would charge
any business um for their zoning fee.
And then the annual um renewal would be
half of that. So it' be 75.
>> Thank you.
>> Any further questions?
>> Hearing none, we thank you for coming
and presenting that information and
thank you for your work on this. And we
have um tonight's the initial reading on
this proposed legislation. We will have
two more readings uh before we move
forward.
Petitions and memorials.
>> There are none this evening. We have
reached the time in uh council's agenda
that uh we have permission of voters and
taxpayers to address council. The rules
are such of permission of voters and
taxpayers that if you have something
that you wish to address to city
council, please come to the podium.
State your name and address and sign the
clipboard. Um you have three minutes to
address council. Um, we will not be
answering questions uh directly from the
floor and your comments must be directed
to council, not members of the audience.
>> Mr. President, members of council, I'm
Bob Levelvel. Uh, reside at 243 East Fth
Avenue. I'm also a member of the parks
board of commissioners. As um some of
you may know, the parks board received a
letter recently uh written by a
longstanding
member of that board and it was
concerning the lack of development of
Bowers Park. I'm here to tell you that
that letter was answered by uh Steve
Gayfield and in there he cites some of
the reasons most of which are not uh
within our control and in that a high
point of that is um him stating that we
have successfully accommodated all
little league baseball in the meantime.
As frustrating as this project is, it's
just like this spring. We had a um
landscaping company out there. Their
equipment showed up and the workers did
not. It's putting us behind even more.
Like I said, most of these things are
out of our control. It reminds me of the
frustrated
pickle ball people of Lancaster years
ago. That project kept getting pushed
back simply because it was considered a
small project and no one would place a
bid. Again, it was out of our control.
Um, we finally did get the job done. If
you've been with me every step of the
way, I mean, there are reasons. I know
if you just drive by the site once a
month or whatever, you'd be going, "What
the heck?" And I understand that. Um
but also remind you I think it was 5
years ago city of Lancaster passed the
tax levy which in part was to fund
rehabilitation of city hall and by all
appearance it looks like that project
after 5 years is just getting started.
So these things can be frustrating. I
think you should understand that on that
basis. I can promise you that that park
will be developed.
Um, and the slowness of it is not due to
negligence.
Quite the opposite. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Do we have anybody else this evening who
would like to address city council
during public comment?
My name is CJ Estelle. Um, I have a
handful of rental properties in the
area. Um, I do not have any short-term
rental properties. Uh, but I do try to
do everything correctly. I try to get
the permits. I try to go through things.
Um, I did acquire a property that was
used as a short-term rental prior to me
getting it. And I understand the
frustration of lack of taxes being
collected, lack of, uh, people following
the processes. um you know that
particular building upon purchasing it,
I wanted to preserve my ability to use
that as a short-term rental. So, I went
through a variance process. Um I I got
the approval for that. Um I again, I
haven't done anything with that. Um but
as we look at the short-term rental
guidelines and things that are here, um
if the primary concern is around we're
not able to collect our tax dollars from
the the lodging tax, I don't see how a
lot of the things that are in this
relate to that. Whether that's a floor
plan, whether that's a background check
for the owners, whether that's a
background check for the managers. Um
there there's a lot of stuff in here
that does not seem related to what the
stated goal is. And it seems like it's a
money grab quite frankly. Um there's,
you know, when I look at the costs of
paying somebody to do floor plans,
paying somebody to uh to do everything
on these these checklists, go through uh
these inspections, go through the filing
fees. Uh and what's to say that you're
not going to to take the next step and
say, you know what, we need a registry
rental for all rentals in in the area.
Um, you know, you guys already have
information about who the owners are
through the the utilities department
with direct contact information. There
are ways to get a hold of people if
there are problems there. Um, you know,
when it comes to uh the the people that
are renting our facilities, um, I do
have short-term rentals in other areas.
I couldn't tell you if somebody's a
registered sex offender. I don't have
that information available to me when
they book my place. Um, I I agree there
may be safety issues, but I I think that
this needs a lot more discussion before
you you can look to pass this as it
stands. Um, I I'll put together a little
bit more thorough of a list and get it
to to one of the council members here um
to to be able to go over it in more
detail. Uh, but I just wanted to voice
my disappointment in reading and and
seeing this and state that I don't think
it accomplishes the goal that you guys
say is the goal of this. Thank you.
Thank you. Is there any other individual
who wishes to address city council this
evening? Seeing none, we thank you for
your attendance at tonight's meeting.
Now move on to um reports of standing
committees.
>> I have finance committee meeting minutes
dated June 26, 2025 submitted by Mr.
Skunberg. Service committee me meeting
minutes dated July 9th, 2025 submitted
by Mr. ALS um serious committee agenda
dated July 11, 2025 submitted by Mr.
Skenover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of
standing committees.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to receive
and file the reports of standing
committees. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Reports of
special committees.
>> I have done this evening.
>> Thank you. We'll now move on to public
hearings. And tonight we have a public
hearing regarding Euing Woods LLC and a
zoning map amendment. The process for
public hearings is that we allow
proponents of the amendment to speak
first and if anybody wants to do that,
they must come to the podium and sign
the clipboard. And after that, we will
hear from opponents of the zoning
amendment. Um, and then we would have a
rebuttal period. If you seek to utilize
a rebuttal or another comment period,
you must have spoken in favor of the
proposed zoning amendment. Um, Law
Director Hall, does that adequately
cover everything we need to?
>> Uh, yes. You can rebut too if you spoke
against it as well.
>> Thank you.
>> Yep. Um, and is there anyone here who
wishes to speak in favor of the Euing
Woods zoning map amendment?
>> Good evening. My name is Chris Tumblin.
I'm a representative of the ownership
group. My address is 250 Civic Center
Drive, Columbus, Ohio. I just want to
give a a quick introduction on on what
we're requesting this evening. Uh, our
entity owns about 52 acres of land. The
proposed 6 acre track that's in the
middle of the 52 acres is what we're
talking about this evening. This
property was acquired after the 52 acres
was uh annexed and reszoned. Um, this
this piece of ground was was acquired to
uh accommodate the entry drive for the
development uh and gives us an
opportunity to control our our front
door. Um the the zoning being proposed
is consistent with the surrounding land
zoning. Um and would appreciate your
support this evening. Happy to answer
any questions that council may have
about the project.
>> And your proposed zoning is
>> uh RM is the proposed zoning.
>> Thank you.
>> Is there anybody else who wishes to
speak in favor of the proposed zoning
map amendment?
Hearing
none, we will now move on to um
opponents of the proposed zoning map
amendment.
Seeing and hearing none, we will um
close the public hearing. But before I
do, are there any questions from any
council members?
Hearing none, we will close the public
hearing on the Euing Woods um zoning map
amendment.
We'll now move on to the reading of
resolutions.
We have no third readings this evening
of resolutions. We will begin with
second reading temporary resolution
5825.
I have a resolution to appropriate from
the undercover balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the law enforcement
block JAG grant police fund 2027
and approve a then and now certificate
for purchases. This is through safety
committee Mr. Bisjack and Miss Tener.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you Mr. President. This will be
the second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings and temporary
resolution 5825.
Temporary resolution 5925.
This is a resolution to appropriate from
the unovered balance and to amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the DOJ equitable
sharing fund 2048
for grant match dollars for the major
crimes unit. Again, this is through
safety committee, Mr. Bisjack and Mr.
Sully.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This will be
the second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings and temporary
resolution 5925.
Temporary resolution 60-25.
A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the 0.45 police fire
and levy 2021 fund 2051 for the purchase
of four police vehicles. Excuse me for
use by the Lancaster Police Department.
Again, this is through safety committee,
Mr. Bisjack and Miss Teter.
>> Council member Bisjack. Thank you, Mr.
President. This will be the second of
three readings. Second of three readings
on temporary resolution 6025.
Temporary resolution 6125.
>> A resolution to schedule Langster City
Council meetings and finance committee
meeting for 2026. This is through law
committee. Mrs. Kates and Mr. Bisch.
>> Council member Kates.
>> Yes. Thank you. Second of three
readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 6125.
Temporary resolution 6225. A resolution
to increase receipts, appropriate from
the unencumbered balance, and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the public transit
fund 2021 and to declare an emergency.
This is through finance committee, Mr.
Skunover and Mr. Als.
>> Council member Skunover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the third reading of temporary
resolution 6225.
>> Second. A motion and second to suspend
to suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary resolution 6225.
Council member Skunover, any discussion
on the motion to ex to suspend?
>> Um, Auditor Nettles, this is the final
close out, if you will, of transit
accounts.
>> Yes, I believe it is. I've got um in
contact with the county that stated the
grant, the final grant that they're
getting a reimbursement for that has to
come through us. This the grant is in
the city's name and um yeah, we've got
all the um rebates that they need from
workers comp and um for that end. So now
we can appropriate those.
>> Perfect. Thank you. All right. We have
no further questions. Please call the
role on the motion to suspend.
>> Mr. Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Lochenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skuner,
>> Mr. Sullie,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> And Mr. W.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolution
6225 passes 9 to zero. Council member
Skunover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record. Temporary
resolution 6225.
>> Second. A motion and a second to pass a
gross enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 6225.
Council member Skunover. Any further
discussion?
>> No sir.
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mrs. Kit,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Locktoberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skoonover,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> And Mr. Wayne,
>> yes.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
6225 passes 9 to zero.
We will now move on to the first reading
of resolutions beginning with temporary
resolution 6325.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to apply for grant
funding from the central Ohio royal
planning organization dedicated funds
program grant to fund right-of-way
acquisition for the memorial pierce
walkways project and to declare an
emergency. This is through public works
committee and Miss Tener and Mr. Luck.
>> Council member Tiner.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the second and third reading of
temporary resolution 6325.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to suspend
the rules and wave the second and third
reading of temporary resolution 6325.
Um, any discussion on the motion to
suspend council member Tiner?
>> Not at this time.
>> Thank you. Um, hearing no further
discussion, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mrs. Kites, yes.
>> Mrs. Coupe.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg.
>> Mr. Skoonover.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Sully.
>> Miss Tener.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wade.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second third reading of temporary
resolution 6325. Passes 9 to zero.
Council member Tener.
>> Yes. I'd like to make a motion that
councilman pass and gross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary resolution
6325.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion. Second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 6325.
Any discussion? Council Member Tiner.
>> Yes. This is a grant we just found out
about and it needs to be in by August
the 8th and it's a a grant money to fund
the right-of-way acquisition for the
Memorial Pierce Walkways project to make
it safe safer for pedestrians around
that area and it also around the
Arlington Avenue also. And uh it's a
$400,000 grant and we will need to pay
80,000 and uh money of 20% so that uh we
can fund the project and that would be a
separate piece of legislation if it
passes tonight.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion from
council hearing? None. Please call the
role.
>> Excuse me. Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. H.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Scooter,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes. Miss Tiner.
>> Yes.
>> And Mr. W.
>> Temporary resolution 6325
passes 9 to zero. Now move on to
temporary resolution 6425.
A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to apply for grant
funding from the central Ohio Royal
Planning Organization dedicated funds
program grant to fund design and
design of and engineering for the
improvements of the campground road and
to declare an emergency. This is your
economic development committee, Mrs.
Hoop and Mrs. Craigs.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Um, yes, Mr. President. And I would like
to make a motion that council suspend
its rules and wave the second and third
reading of temporary resolution 64-25.
>> Second.
>> A motion and a second to suspend the
rules and wave the second and third
reading of temporary resolution 6425.
Uh any discussion on the motion to
suspend council member
>> just that the deadline is August 8th.
>> Thank you. Hearing no further
discussion, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als Mr. Bisjek. Yes.
>> Mrs. Kra. Yes.
>> Mrs. H.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Lenberg.
>> Mr. Mer.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Sully.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. W.
>> Motion to suspend the rules. Wait the
second third reading of temporary
resolution 6425 passes 9 to zero.
Council member Hoop.
>> Um. Yes. Mr. President. I would like to
make a motion that council passing and
gross and enter upon the written record
tempor
temporary resolution 64-25.
>> Second.
>> A motion. Second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 6425. Any further discussion
on the
>> No, we discussed it in finance. So,
>> thank you. Uh, hearing no further
discussion, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mrs. Kra, yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luenberg,
>> Mr. Scoover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Ter, yes. And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Temporary resolution 6425 passes 9 to
zero. Temporary resolution 6525.
A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and to amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the city income tax
fund 2016
to accommodate increased refunds in 2025
and to pay to replace the backup server
for the income tax department with a
cloud-based system. This is through
finance committee Mr. Skunover and Mr.
Sully.
>> Council member Skunover.
>> It's a first of three readings. First of
three readings on temporary resolution
6525.
Temporary resolution 6625.
>> A resolution stating the services to be
provided by the municipal corporation to
annex territory of Mark A and Beth A.
Powers for the expedited type 2
annexation of partial number 014 0112500
011 23 0 014
0 1 02 or 42 0 0 1 0 0 1 4 0 1 0 1 500 0
and 0 1 4112501
consisting of 163.60 609 plus or minus
acres in Greenville Township and to
declare an emergency. This is through
economic development committee. Mrs.
Hoop and Mr. Wing.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Yes, Mr. President. I would like to make
a motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the second and third readings
um of temporary resolution 66-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to suspend
the rules and wave the second and third
readings of temporary resolution 6625.
And to note, I think I'm speaking for
clerk Scott, I think she will be happy
that she doesn't have to do a second and
third reading. Any further discussion on
the motion to suspend
>> hearing? None. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kes,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lochenberg,
>> Mr. Scoover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wing,
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second and third reading of temporary
resolution 6625 passes 9 to zero.
Council member who?
>> Oh, yes. Mr. President, I would like to
make a motion that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record.
Temporary resolution 66-25.
>> Second.
>> A motion second to pass and engross and
enter upon the written record. Temporary
resolution 6625.
Any further discussion?
>> No.
>> Director Hall.
>> Just briefly, President Porter, I wanted
to um recognize that Zack Walker from
the Plank Law Firm is here in case
anybody has questions. Um, I don't think
he was able to make it in time for
finance committee, but he is here now in
case anybody has any questions for him.
So, thank you for being here tonight.
Zach,
>> are there any questions from council
members regarding the annexation?
>> I don't hear any. So, we thank you for
coming and attending this evening's
meeting. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bisch, yes.
>> Mrs. Kates,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Spooner,
>> Mr. Sie,
>> yes.
>> Miss Ter,
>> And Mr. Wayne.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary resolution
6625 passes 9 to zero. We'll now move on
to the reading of ordinances. We have no
third readings this evening. So we move
to second readings beginning with
temporary ordinance 2725.
>> Sorry. an ordinance creating five
incentive districts and declaring
improvements to certain real property
within the incentive districts to be a
public purpose and exempt from real
property taxation. Identifying certain
public infrastructure improvements that
once will once made will benefit or
serve the parcels in the incentive
districts requiring the owners of those
parcels to make service payments in lie
of taxes. establishing an incentive
district public improvement tax
increment equivalent fund for the
deposit of such services authorizing
payments to the Lancaster City School
Districts and approving related matters.
This is through economic development
committee. Mrs. Hoop and Mr. Wing.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. And I
would like to make a motion that council
suspend its rules and wave the third
reading of temporary ordinance 27-25.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary ordinance 2725.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> No.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion from
council?
>> Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bishack, yes.
>> Mrs. Kes,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoops,
>> yes. Mr. Lochenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Scooter,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> Mr. Wink,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary ordinance
2725 passes 9 to zero. Council member
Hoop.
>> Mr. President, I would like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 21 27-25.
Second.
>> A motion a second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 2725.
Any discussion? Council member.
>> Um this is just the developers tiff at
Powers Run off of 188.
>> Thank you. Any discussion from council
members?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bishop, yes.
>> Mrs. Kes, yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> Mr. Scooter,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sie,
>> yes. Miss Ter and Mr. Wing.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record. Uh temporary
ordinance 2725 passes 9 to zero.
Temporary ordinance 2825.
>> An ordinance declaring the improvement
to certain real property located in the
city of Lancaster, Ohio to be public
purpose declaring such improvement to be
exempt from real property taxation
pursuant to Ohio Revised Code section
5709.40B
40B requiring the owners thereof to make
annual service payments in lie of taxes.
Describing the public infrastructure
improvements to be made that will
directly benefit the real property
establishing a public improvement tax
increment equivalent fund for the
deposit of service payments together
with relation with related
authorizations. This again is through
economic development committee Mrs. Hoop
and Mrs. Council member Hoop.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass, engross, and enter
upon the written record temporary
ordinance 28-25.
>> We're on second. We're on second of
three readings.
>> Oh, darn it. I'm sorry. I was just
assuming there were all two readings.
>> Nope, you're all good.
>> Just joking.
>> All right, we're on second and three
readings on temporary ordinance 2825.
Temporary ordinance 2925,
>> an ordinance declaring that the
improvement to certain real property
located in the city of Lancaster, Ohio
to be a public purpose, declaring such
improvement to be exempt from real
property taxation pursuant to the Ohio
Revised Code section 5709.40B
40B requiring the owners thereof to make
annual service payments in lie of taxes.
Describing the public infrastructure
improvements to be made that will be
directly benefit the the real property
establishing a public improvement tax
increment equivalent fund for the
deposit of service payments together
with related authorizations. Again, this
economic development committee, Mrs.
Hoop, and Mr. Scooter.
Second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
ordinance 2925.
Temporary ordinance 3025.
>> An ordinance declaring the improvement
to certain real property located in the
city of Lancaster, Ohio to be a public
purpose declaring such improvement to be
exempt from real property taxation
pursuant to a higher revised code
section 5709.40B
requiring the owners thereof to make
annual service payments in low of taxes.
describing the public infrastructure
improvements to be made that will
directly benefit the real property.
Establishing a public improvement tax
increment equivalent fund for the
deposit of service payments together
with related authorizations. This is
through economic development committee.
Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. Crates.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
ordinance uh 3025. We will now move on
to the first reading of ordinances
beginning with temporary ordinance 3125.
>> Um, ordinance, oh, I'm sorry, an
ordinance to amend the Lancaster
codified ordinance part 11 planning and
zoning title 3 zoning and property
restrictions and to adopt chapter 1131
short-term rentals. This is through code
enforcement code enforcement and zoning
committee. Mr. Sully and Mrs. Hoop.
>> Council member Sully.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This will be
the first of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 3125.
Temporary ordinance 3225.
An ordinance to accept the annexation of
point
0.605 plus or minus acres in Pleasant
Township and to declare an emergency.
The sister economic development
committee Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. Crates.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> First of two readings.
>> First of two readings on temporary
ordinance 3225.
Temporary Ordinance 3325,
>> an ordinance to amend the zoning map
subject to passage of the annexation of
0.605 plus or minus acres in the
Pleasant Township and to declare an
emergency. Again, this is your economic
development committee, Mrs. Hoop and Mr.
Wing.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Um, first of first of two readings.
>> First of two readings on temporary
ordinance 3325.
Temporary ordinance 3425.
an ordinance to accept a petition for
the expedited type 2 annexation of
163.6098
plus or minus acres in the Greenfield
Township to consent to annexation and to
declare an emergency. This is through
economic development committee Mr. Mrs.
Hoop and Mr. Wing
>> also to provide a buffer for
incompatible
land use pursuant to Ohio Revised Code
709.023C 023C and to declare an
emergency. Council member who
>> we're still on 34-25,
right?
>> We're on 3425. That's correct.
>> Okay. Just making sure. Um Mr.
President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the second and three third readings of
temporary ordinance 34-25.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
suspend the rules and wave the second
and third reading of temporary ordinance
3425.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> No. Thank you.
>> Please call the roll.
>> Mr. Als? Yes.
>> Mr. Bishek? Yes.
>> Mrs. K?
>> Yes.
>> Mrs. Hoot?
>> Mr. Luenberg?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Skunover?
>> Mr. Sully?
>> Yes.
>> Miss Tiner?
>> Mr. Wing?
>> Yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules. Wave the
second third reading of temporary
ordinance 3425 passes 9 to zero. Council
member Hoop.
>> Yes, Mr. President. And I'd like to make
a motion that council pass engross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 34-25.
>> Second.
>> A motion and second to pass gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 3425. Any discussion?
>> Um, not at this time.
>> Thank you. Um, please call a role.
>> Mr. A, yes. Mr. Bishack, yes. Mrs. K,
yes. Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luenberg,
>> Mr. Skunver,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner, yes. And Mr. Yes.
>> Motion to to pass engross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary ordinance
3425 passes 9 to zero. Temporary
ordinance 3525.
I have an ordinance to amend permanent
ordinance 49-24,
the Fairfield County Municipal Court
Management and Professional Pay
ordinance, and to declare an emergency.
This is through administrative
committee, Mr. Luckenberg and Mr.
Bisjack.
>> Council member Luckenberg.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. President. I'd like
to make a motion that council suspend
its rules and wave the second and third
readings of ordinance temporarily
numbered uh 3525.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second to
suspend the rules and wave the second.
Third reading of temporary ordinance
3525. Any discussion on the motion to
suspend?
>> Uh, yes. These responsibilities of this
new hire directly impact the law
director's office and so we're that's
why we're requesting suspension of the
second third readings so they can
proceed with hiring process.
>> Thank you.
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mrs. Kes, yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> Mr. Skuniver,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner, yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes. Motion to suspend the rules and
wave the second and third reading of
temporary ordinance 3525 passes 9 to
zero. Council member Luckenberg.
>> Uh Mr. President, I'd like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
then enter upon the written record
ordinance temporarily numbered 3525.
>> Second. A motion a second to pass gross
and enter upon the written record
temporary ordinance 3525. Any further
discussion on
>> uh not at this time.
>> Okay. Thank you. Please call a role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisch,
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> yes. Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luenberg,
>> Mr. Skunberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Si,
>> Miss Ter,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. W.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary ordinance
3525 passes 9 to zero. There is no
tabled legislation up uh this evening.
Unfinished business. We have none at
this time. We'll now move on to new
business. We have two items listed in
new business at this time. Um, beginning
with a liquor license.
>> I have a new liquor license for the
OXB's LLC. I'm doing business at 1732
East Main Street and I've sent the
information off to the law director
along with the um the police department
for background.
>> Yes. Thank you, ma'am. So, um, Oxbs has
been over on the east side of town for
some time. They're in a temporary
facility. You may all have seen that. Um
kind of a food truck situation. Hoping
to move into uh the Ponderosa end of the
um strip mall there um and open a a
permanent full-time restaurant. Um but
the whenever somebody applies for a
liquor license, there is a background
check done. The background check was
provided to the Lancaster Police
Department. Um, Deputy Chief Kaitton
actually um went through that
information for me and then also um
entered the individual's names in the uh
city's CAD, our our dispatch information
system basically, and was unable to find
any any negative um things associated
with either the names of the owners or
with the address there where Ox is
currently located. So, um, on the public
safety side, neither myself nor the
police department see any reason to to
oppose the issuance of a new liquor
permit for this business and just wanted
to make you all aware so you can vote
one way or the other. Thanks.
>> Thank you. So, can we entertain a motion
to allow the issuance of
>> Okay. So, we have a motion pending. Do
we have a second to allow the issuance?
>> Second.
>> We have a second. A motion in a second.
Uh all those in favor uh for allowing
the issuance of the proposed liquor
license, please signify by saying I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Thank you.
We now move on to we have two new
appointments as alluded to in the
finance committee meeting by the mayor
uh of individuals to the BCA. Um Mr.
James is in in the audience now and we
appreciate his service and Miss Anderson
is in Chicago with a new baby
grandchild. So I will entertain a motion
to make these two appointments to the
BZA. Um do we have a a motion? So move,
Mr. President. Council member Bisjack
and second, Council Member Skunover. All
those in favor of the appointments,
please signify by saying I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Um, thank
you uh for those appointments and thank
you for your willingness to serve on the
BCA. It serves an important function.
Um, are there is there any new business
from council members this evening that
you would like to bring before council?
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Uh, Council Member Als,
>> I would like to read a letter uh that
was presented to the uh parks board um
by Judith Edwards who served as a park
park board member for 35 years. So, I I
think we should listen to what she has
to say. Um it's addressed to the members
of the board. This letter is written to
you as concurrent commissioners of the
Langster Park board commissioners to
share my concerns regarding the lack of
development of Bowowers Memorial Park.
It has been more than six years since
the city accepted the donation of 20
plus acres of land from D. Merryill
Bowers for development into Bowowers
Memorial Park. As you may know, I was
instrumental in encouraging this
donation from Mr. hours while I was a
member of the park board and worked with
several superintendents to complete the
donation. Is it is an extreme
disappointment to me that the park board
has failed to move this forward with the
development of the Bowowers Memorial
Park originally envisioned as a
replacement sports baseball park for
Miller Park which the city threatened
and is now completed changing into the
city water department plant. New ball
new ball diamonds were a pri priority.
Although Mr. Bowers believed moving
baseball diamonds to his donated land
would solve the need for diamond
relocation and the parks department
developed a plan for installation of
ballfield complex. Mr. Bowers did not
restrict his donation to the use of only
ballfields. Shortly after the donation
was accepted, there was an article in
the Eagle Gazette about the donations
and plans for the new work. Mike Tharp
was quoted as saying the park should be
ready for use by 2021.
Obviously, this did not happen. The
legal ownership documents require the
land donated by Mr. Bowers and accepted
by the city be used only as a public
park and until development of the
property conveyed to to be used only as
open green space for agricultural
purposes. The bark the park board has
failed to follow through with the
original plan and by stopping midway in
its regrading efforts is not using the
land as open green space for agriculture
purposes thus thwarting Mr. Bower's
intentions. I do understand the issues
faced by the park board for this
project. Co intervention changes
superintendent diversion of funds when
the purchase development of General
Sherman property was undertaken. But six
years is a long time to wait to see some
activity on a previously conceived
project. In addition, the suspension of
the initial grading of the property has
left the property in an unsightly and
deplorable condition and an eyesore to
the neighborhood.
Over the years since the donation, I
have spoken to Mike Thurp and Steve
Gayfield about this project with various
explanations giving for the delay in the
development and assurances that the
property is still going to be developed.
While I still believe there is a need
for more baseball diamonds the city if a
different use if a different park use of
this land is considered more desirable.
I urge you to move forward and at least
restore the property to a cleaner more
pleasant look but preferably to timely
develop Bowowers Park into a park that
will be a benefit to the community. I
also bring to your attention the
donation of $78647
that was made to friends of the parks in
finalization of the Bowowers estate and
from the memorial donations made by
friends to be used as a plaque on the
propo proposed shelter house with the
inscription this property donated by D
Mel Bowers for the enjoyment of the
community. I hope that the friends of
the parks have earmarked these funds for
the purpose and someday in the
foreseeable future such a plaque can be
installed.
It is a deterrent to future potential
donors when accepting a gift. The park
board fails to follow through with the
stated intentions in part motivated the
gift. I urge you to honor the donation
of Mr. Bowers by prioritizing the
development of the land he donated into
a park for the community good. signed
Judith Edwards. Now, the reason I'm
reading this tonight is I need to
explain this a little background. I I've
been on the board I've been on city
council for almost three years for the
second time. I've attended 90% of the
park board meetings. I I've heard all of
the reasons that the park hasn't been
developed.
And
I'm not accepting any of them. They
sound a lot like excuses that are
repeated over and over and over and over
again.
Um, primarily
they there was an agreement with the um
Ohio engineers.
They used it as a training facility for
equipment operators and they were going
to do the excavation in the park for
free
in exchange for diesel fuel.
Well, it's not getting done. I have I
I've been back on council for three
years. I've seen very little if any
earth moved at Bowowers Park.
The the real reason that I wanted to
read this to you is I'm not really sure
that anyone on this council would have
ever seen this letter if I hadn't been
at the park board meeting and got a copy
of it.
And another reason that I think it's
important is that in the May meeting of
the park board, the president of the
park board looked me square in the eye
when I asked him about Bowers Park and
said if it were up to me, I would not
spend a penny on Bowowers Park.
So some flags went up.
I three years I patiently attended
meetings, patiently listened
and then heard that and I said, "Okay,
what I'm doing is not working.
So, I need to do something else." So,
this is part of me doing something else.
You need to understand that if you are
serious about developing Bowowers Park,
you need to step up. you need to do
something. And what I'm proposing, and I
asked the law director for an opinion,
and she told me today that she doesn't
see any reason why we couldn't do this,
but the only power that I see that we
have over the park board is through the
budget.
Well, when you lump the budget, when
when we vote on the budget, we vote on
the entire city budget. So, do you want
to be the guy that says no because
you're unhappy with one piece of the
budget? And I don't want to be that guy.
So, what I'm going to propose is that we
vote on the park budget separately.
And we hold our feet to the fire. And if
there isn't money in the budget,
sufficient money to move this project
forward once and for all, we should veto
their budget.
They earmarked $75,000
for Bowers Park this year. It is July
the 14th and they have spent zero
dollars
on that park this year.
So,
I just want to get that out there. I
want to make the the the letter part of
public record. And thank you.
Thank you, Council Member Als. Uh the
letter will be made part of the council
minutes for this evening. Do we have any
further comments by council members and
new business? Council member Tener.
>> Yes. Last uh April I made a video and I
posted online got over 30,000 views of
Bowowers Park. I'm going to go out
tomorrow and make another one to show
you nothing has changed. Uh one of the
reasons I'm glad that Mr. Alen brought
this up because I'd been I have attended
parks board meetings before and I was at
a parks board meeting and it was quite a
healthy discussion. I was there
complaining about something that needed
to be had tension brought to and none of
what I said it just showed that I was in
attendance. It did not one thing I said
was in that and nobody everybody that
knows me I never go any place without
saying something. So uh something should
have been in there. It was a pretty
healthy discussion. And that's kind of
why I just think that the parks board I
had asked before when shuffler was to
remove the people because I could see
how things weren't being right by the
taxpayers. And that's why I was also
against the permanent tax levy for the
um parks because I I don't think a
permanent levy always helps because you
can't hold their feet to the fire
because then they can do whatever they
want. So I'm uh with you on that.
>> Thank you. Thank you for your comments.
Any other comments from council members
at this time?
hearing none. Um I just wanted to um put
forth that in new business going
forward, there's going to be an agenda
change. I will be asking for each
committee chair to give a brief update
of their committee activities or when
their next upcoming meeting is. Um we're
just going to be working to increase our
education as council members and our
transparency. So keep that in mind for
our next council meeting. you'll have a
brief. If you don't have an update, if
you don't have any legislation pending,
you can pass and say, "Our next meeting
is whatever date. Um, but if you do have
something significant, that's come
forward before your committee." We'll
give you an opportunity to discuss that
and bring it forward before council. We
can all read your minutes, but I think
also hearing it is helpful for our
folks. So, just that note. Now, we'll
move on to the announcements of
scheduled meetings. I have next regular
sessions of council August 11, 2025 at
6:30 p.m. here in council chambers.
August 25th, 2025 at 6:30 p.m. in
council chambers.
>> Any special scheduled meetings?
>> I have none.
>> Regularly scheduled committee meetings.
>> I have five of them. I have
administrative services committee
uh July 16th at 800 a.m. City Hall 1897
conference room. Code Enforcement
Committee meeting on July 17th at 7:30
a.m. City Hall 1897 conference room.
Water water pollution control service
committee July 21st 1st at 7:30 a.m.
City Hall 1897 conference room. Economic
Development Committee meeting July 24th
at 7:30 a.m. City Hall 1897 conference
room in the safety committee found on
August 8th at 8 a.m. City Hall 1897
conference room.
>> Thank you. Reading of bills.
>> I have two of them for MNCO. Um it's
one's for $58.60.
The other one's for $133.16.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to pay the bills.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and second to pay the
bills. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. No need
for an executive session. I will now
entertain a motion to adjurnn.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
we adjourn.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion a second to adjurnn.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Thank you. Tonight's meeting is
adjourned. Please remember to sign your
legislation. And also to everybody, uh,
thank you for attending tonight. And our
next council meeting will be August
11th. We're on a brief recess uh due to
the festival. So, thank you
[Music]
[Applause]